Finding Aid for Karl L. Zinn papers, 1964-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Topical Files
  - International Congress on Technology Assessment (ISTA)
    - Project Report, Telecommunications at the Second International ISTA Congress: An Experiment in Extending Technical Communications through Computer-based Conferencing in Association with Professional Meetings June 14, 1979 (Box 15)
    - Solar, background files circa 1977 (Box 15)
  - Inter-University Committee on Instructional Use of Computers (IUCIUC)
    - Ad hoc Committee on the Instructional Uses of Computers 1965 (Box 15)
    - Background and General Files 1966 (Box 15)
    - Proposal draft, " The Prototype Development of a Computer-based Educational Network between Three Universities," November 22, 1965 (Box 15)
  - Instructional Technology General Counsel, charge and membership circa 1988 (Box 15)
  - Journal articles on CONFER circa 1984 (Box 15)
  - LIPS (Languages for Interactive Problem Solving), meeting materials circa 1972 (Box 15)
  - MAD.I: ConComp: Research in Conversational Use of Computers November 1966 (Box 15)
  - MERIT
    - Addendum to a Proposal to Office of Computing Activities National Science Foundation April 1969 (Box 15)
    - Barr's Report on Long-Range Planning for MERIT January 28, 1975 (Box 15)
    - Brainstorming March 25, 1975 (Box 15)
    - Brochure circa 1974 (Box 15)
    - Chronicle of Merit's Early History October 22, 1997 (Box 15)
    - Director March 1974 (Box 15)
    - Director's Advisory Committee 1975 (Box 15)
    - Educational Computing at the University of Michigan: A Survey of Activities and Resources April 22, 1974 (Box 15)
    - Facilities and Resources, guide and background materials circa 1975 (Box 15)
    - History of MERIT Computer Network November 13, 1974 (Box 15)
    - Identification of Instructional Needs and Potential Uses of an Interuniversity Computing Network in the State of Michigan March 1970 (Box 15)
    - Legislative presentation January 1968 (Box 15)
    - Letter for Workshops undated (Box 15)
    - Memorandum to C. Overberger circa 1975 (Box 15)
    - Memorandum to Staff 1972-1974 (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous Files 1974-1975 (Box 15)
    - Papers
      - Development of Applications for the Merit Computing Network, June 1972 (Box 15)
      - Development of Applications for the MERIT Computer Network: Enhancement of Selected Resources circa 1974 (Box 15)
    - Planning, general materials, Fall 1974 (Box 15)
    - Project Description (Box 15)
    - Proposal (MERIT)
      - Background and General Files
        - 1967 (Box 15)
        - 1968 (Box 16)
        - 1969 (Box 16)
      - Expanding the Facilities of the MERIT Computer Networks December 1973 (Box 16)
      - Prototype Network of Users of Computers for Self-Instruction and Teaching November 15, 1970 (Box 16)
      - Unique Resources at Merit Host Computing Center February 1970 (Box 16)
      - Proposal Summary February 1970 (Box 16)
    - Proposed Budget circa 1971 (Box 16)
    - Publication
      - MAL (MERIT Assembly Language) User's Guide and Link11 User's Guide July 1971 (Box 16)
    - Reports
      - Educational Computing at the University of Michigan: A Survey of Activities and Resources, 1973-1974 (Box 16)
      - Educational Computing at the University of Michigan: A Survey of Activities and Resources 1976-1977 (Box 16)
      - Progress Report July 1969-March 1971 (Box 16)
      - Progress on Applications Development, 1970-1971 (Box 16)
    - Site Visit April 1968 (Box 16)
    - Survey of University of Michigan Users 1974 (Box 16)
    - Workshop June 1970 (Box 16)
  - MICIS (Michigan Inter-University Committee on Information Systems)
    - Agendas and Meeting Minutes 1973-1975 (Box 16)
    - Association of Public Data Users April 1976 (Box 16)
    - Background Materials circa 1973, undated (Box 16)
    - Computing Resources Directory undated (Box 16)
    - Directory of Unique Learning Resources for Higher Education in Michigan October 1975 (Box 16)
    - Extensions Task Force circa 1966 (Box 16)
    - Exxon Proposal January 1976 (Box 16)
    - General Files
      - 1966-1967 (Box 16)
      - 1968-1970 (Box 16)
      - 1974 (Box 16)
    - Library Consortium 1972, undated (Box 16)
    - Membership circa 1975, undated (Box 16)
    - Program Exchange circa 1976 (Box 16)
    - Project Statement 1967-1969 (Box 17)
    - Proposals circa 1967-1975 (Box 17)
    - Report
      - Original MICIS Report, April 2, 1970 (Box 17)
      - Task Force on Instructional Programs and Educational Technology 1975 (Box 17)
    - Staff Organization circa 1968 (Box 17)
  - Michigan Information System (MIS) Task Force and Advisory Committee circa 1969 (Box 17)
  - Michigan Terminal System (MTS) Manual 1987 (Box 17)
  - Network Examples, Concepts and Profiles circa 1972 (Box 17)
  - Networks for Knowledge
    - 1966-1968 undated (Box 17)
    - 1970 (Box 17)
  - Notes on Potential Users of Computer Aided Instruction (CAI) 1970 (Box 17)
  - ON-LINE, general files, 1974-1978 (Box 17)
  - On-line Computer Conference on Conferencing May 21, 1975 (Box 17)
  - Organizer February 1977 (Box 17)
  - Papers
    - Brief History of Computers in Teaching and Learning Activities, circa 1974 (Box 17)
    - Instructional Uses of the Computer in Higher Education March 1971 (Box 17)
    - Planning and Control of Computing Resources, Charles Mossmann, September 1973 (Box 17)
    - Questions and Comments About MTS: Forum, Jeff Ogden, May 1979 (Box 17)
  - Pittsburgh Interactive Language (PIL)
    - General Files 1971-1974 (Box 17)
    - Primer 1971 (Box 17)
    - Report, Volume 12: PIL/2 in MTS December 1974 (Box 17)
  - PLATO computer-based education (CBE) system March 1975 (Box 17)
  - Programming Languages and the Field of Law 1974 (Box 17)
  - Project EXTEND (Extending University Computing Resources into College Learning Activities)
    - Advisory Committee Meeting Minutes
      - 1971 (Box 17)
      - 1972 (Box 17)
    - An Aid to Documentation 1971 (Box 17)
    - Annotated Table of Contents for Program Documentation circa 1971 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, general circa 1972 (Box 17)
    - Demonstrations of Instructional Computing in Project Extend circa 1974 (Box 17)
    - Distribution List for Project Extend undated (Box 17)
    - Information Sheet 1972-1974 (Box 17)
    - Information and Program Exchange Services 1970-1973 (Box 17)
    - Instructions for Using the Datel or UCC Terminal undated (Box 17)
    - Extending University Computing Resources into College Learning Activities circa 1972-1974 (Box 17)
    - Flyers circa 1972 (Box 17)
    - General Files circa 1970-1975 (Box 18)
    - Help Files undated (Box 18)
    - News from Project EXTEND circa 1972 (Box 18)
    - Notes on SPAN: Programs circa 1972 (Box 18)
    - Procedures and Guidelines for Participating Institutions circa 1972 (Box 18)
    - Program Descriptions circa 1972 (Box 18)
    - Programming Languages circa 1971 (Box 18)
    - Progress Reports, January and July 1972 (Box 18)
    - Publications
      - Instructional Uses of Interactive Computer Systems, September 1968 (Box 18)
      - Program Logic Manual for MAL (Merit Assembly Language) July 1971 (Box 18)
      - Research News scattered dates (1964 1970, 1985 1990) (Box 18)
      - A Short Guide to MTS and Remote Terminal Operation, circa 1972 (Box 18)
    - Referral Service April 1975 (Box 18)
    - Reports
      - Appropriation Request for a Computer Network to Improve Learning and Teaching, a. 1967-1968 (Box 18)
      - Building Program for the Proposed Michigan Information Center December 1965 (Box 18)
      - Comparative Study of Languages for Programming Interactive Use of Computers in Instruction 1969 (Box 18)
    - Tables of Languages and Support August 1971 (Box 18)
    - Work Plan circa 1971-1973 (Box 18)
  - Proposals
    - Concomp: Research in Conversational Use of Computers, March 1965 (Box 18)
    - Effectiveness and Efficiency of Selected Technology Assessment Methodology, undated (Box 18)
    - Exxon proposal, background materials February 1975 (Box 18)
    - Multi-disciplinary Faculty Workshops on Development of Computer-based Gaming and Simulation in College Teaching March 1975 (Box 18)
    - Proposal for a New Data Concentrator, December 1970 (Box 18)
    - Telecommunications at the Second International ISTA Congress: An Experiment in Extending Technical Communications through Computer-based Conferencing in Association with Professional Meetings March 29, 1976 (Box 18)
  - Progress Report A Computer-based System to Enhance Sharing of Technical Information in a System of Scientific Communities, January 26, 1977 (Box 18)
  - Publications
    - Computers in Teaching and Learning Activities: A Sourcebook on Resource Sharing Among Colleges and Universities, 1975 (Box 18)
    - Computing Report in Science and Engineering, November-December 1969 (Box 18)
    - Reprints, Karl Zinn circa 1969-1976 (Box 18)
  - Reports
    - Computer-based System to Enhance Sharing of Technical Information in a System of Scientific Communities, March 17, 1968 (Box 18)
    - An Evaluative Review of Uses of Computers in Instruction Project CLUE (Computer Learning Under Evaluation) December 1970 (Box 18)
    - An Introduction to FOIL (File-Oriented Interpretive Language) Programming in NTS May 1971 (Box 18)
    - Information Processing Systems as a Basis of Learning Environments, December 10, 1970 (Box 18)
    - Report on Machine Computation at the University of Michigan November 12, 1964 (Box 18)
  - Reports (cont.)
    - Reports by Working Group for the Information Infrastructure July 1992 (Box 18)
  - Seminar on Information Systems and Simulations in Medical Education February 1975 (Box 19)
  - Small Grant Proposal, application background material 1969 (Box 19)
  - State of Michigan, planning materials 1965-1966 (Box 19)
  - State of Michigan, technical committee 1965-1966 (Box 19)
  - Statistical Systems and Databases Working Group circa 1970 (Box 19)
  - Survey of Instructional Computing at the University of Michigan November 1981 (Box 19)
  - Technical Reports (Concomp)
    - PDP-8/338 Executive System June 1967 (Box 19)
    - Engineering Assistant: Design of a Symbol Manipulation System August 1967 (Box 19)
    - Engineering Design Report: PDP-7/Modified 338 Display Interface August 1967 (Box 19)
  - Teleconferencing circa 1975 (Box 19)
  - Telnet, background materials circa 1977 (Box 19)
  - University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (UCCPU)
    - Ad hoc Subcommittee on Instructional Software circa 1972 (Box 19)
    - Computer Funds, general files circa 1975 (Box 19)
    - Instructional Uses for Computers (Subcommittee)
      - 1966-1967 (Box 19)
      - 1970-1972, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Katz circa 1965 (Box 19)
    - Meeting Agenda and Materials
      - 1966 (Box 19)
      - 1970-1972 (Box 19)
      - 1975 (Box 19)
      - Recommendations for Action and Further Study Regarding Instructional Use of Computers at the University 1970-1971 (Box 19)
    - Requests 1972 (Box 19)
    - Steering Committee Meeting Materials 1970 (Box 19)
    - University Subcommittee on Academic Computing (Box 19)
    - 1984 (Box 19)
    - Report of the Advisory Task Force on Computing Center Access May 18, 1984 (Box 19)
    - Strategic Directions and Initiatives 1984-1987 September 15, 1984 (Box 19)
  - UM-Apple Contract, remarks made to the Executive Officers December 7, 1983 (Box 19)
- User Reference Documentation
  The User Reference Documentation series (1 linear foot, 1971-1988) is comprised of support documentation written for various users, administrators, faculty and students of the CONFER system. The earliest guide, " CONFER Guide, A Guide for the Computer-Conference Organizer," dates to 1975. Guides in the subseries range from small pocket-size guides to full instructional manuals.
  - Autonote User's Manual July 20, 1971 (Box 20)
  - A Basic Software Package for the Computek Terminal on MTS August 1971 (Box 20)
  - Computer Terminals For Education August 15, 1973 (Box 20)
  - Educational Information Network January 14, 1968 (Box 20)
  - Concomp, Data Concentrator User's Guide April 1970 (Box 20)
  - CONFER
    - The Beginner's Guide to CONFER II 1986 (Box 20)
    - Computer-based Educational Communications at the University of Michigan February 25, 1976 (Box 20)
    - Faculty Workshop 1987 (Box 20)
    - "Green" Guide to CONFER II circa 1979 (Box 20)
    - A Guide for the Computer-Conference Organizer September 15, 1975 (Box 20)
    - Instructional Documentation circa 1976 (Box 20)
    - Instruction Guide 1987 and not dated (Box 20)
    - Instructor Guide for Class Use of Confer February 8, 1988 (Box 20)
    - An Introduction to Computer-based Conferencing November 22, 1976 (Box 20)
    - Notes for Busy Users of CONFER circa 1989 and not dated (Box 20)
    - Notes for Organizers of Class Conferences Using CONFER on MTS December 3, 1985 (Box 20)
    - Notes from the On-line Documentation October 30, 1975 (Box 20)
    - Organizer's Guide to CONFER II, A CRLT Workshop February 1984 (Box 20)
    - Organizing a Computer-based Conference: A Guide for Persons Using CONFER on MTS circa 1978, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Pocket Guides to CONFER Computer-Aided Communication 1976-1977 (Box 20)
    - Pocket Guide for the ISTA Congress October 24-28, 1976 (Box 20)
    - Quick Start Reference Guides to Confer II circa 1986 (Box 20)
    - Support Packet September 1988 (Box 20)
    - Tutorial 1976 (Box 20)
    - User's Guide to CONFER II July 1985 (Box 20)
  - Conference on Instructional Computing March 2-3, 1973 (Box 20)
  - HAL2 Manual July 1975 (Box 20)
  - List of Information Technology Instruction Advisors November 1981 (Box 20)
  - Merit Reference Shelf circa 1971 (Box 20)
  - Microcomputers at the University of Michigan circa 1978 (Box 20)
  - Mini and Microcomputer Interaction with MTS January 1981 (Box 20)
  - Presentations at the CRLT Faculty Seminar circa 1979 (Box 20)
  - Reference Guides
    - For Using Silent 700 Terminal on MTS undated (Box 20)
    - For Using Portacom Terminal on MTS undated (Box 20)
  - Progress Report, A Computer-based System to Enhance Sharing of Technical Information in a System of Scientific Communities January 26, 1977 (Box 20)
  - Reports
    - Computer-based Educational Communications at the University of Michigan February 25, 1976 (Box 20)
    - Group Viewing of Interactive Computer Output: A Description of Techniques and Devices August 1972 (Box 20)
    - Means for Student Access to Computers: An Outline February 1971 (Box 20)
    - Riding the Wave of the New Information Technologies: The Administrator's Role November 1981 (Box 20)
  - Seminar on Personal Home Computers in Teaching and Scholarly Work, Spring 1979 (Box 20)
  - Survey of Instructional Computing at the University of Michigan November 1, 1981 (Box 20)
Summary of CONFER Session print-outs
This list was compiled using similar lists located in the manuscripts and by reading through the purpose statements for many of the CONFER sessions. Note that over time, certain conventions evolved within CONFER including a brief welcome message that included a statement on the scope of the conference.
The names given for the CONFERs were based on a scheme that aimed to start all class conferences with a sequence of numbers (e.g. 2Q1A:Argue) and that included CRLT as the pre-fix for all conferences facilitated by Center for Learning and Teaching staff. Other conventions draw on the use of acronyms (e.g. CAP for Computer Assistance Program of the Political Science Department, ISTA for International Science Technology Assessment) and other abbreviations such as TA for Technology Assessment, Word for Microsoft Word, and MICRO for Microcomputers.
[CONFER descriptions and notes drawn from CONFER U Conferences, Information Technology Digest, http://www.itd.umich.edu/ITDigest/0997/feat01side02.html; Robert Parnes dissertation, “Learning to CONFER: The Interplay of Theory and Practice in Computer Conferencing”; Anne Gilliland-Swetland, Gregory Kinney, William Wallach, Final Report to the NHPRC, December 1992; and from reading through a number of the CONFERS. }
1J3A:PEACE Conference for a class taught by Professor Dick Mann. Professor Mann states the purpose of the confer is to "Use this item to accumulate general reactions to the whole notion of PEACE itself."
2GDB181:Staff CONFER for a computer science course. Professor Aaron Finerman.
2Q1A:Argue Class conference that includes discussion not limited to classroom topics but includes current events and comments on campus situations. Professor Dick Meisler.
5BZA:N830 Nursing 830 taught by Professor Ruth Barnard.
K556:OLD MAGNA Conference for persons interested in developing games and related phenomena.
K9JK:UTEPSEM Class conference. Professor Allan Feldt.
AIGP: FORUM Discussion on uses, trends and ethical issues involving artificial intelligence.
ARCH:FORUM Discussion on architecture and use of technology.
BAD:IDEA Class project for RC 45 Linguistics and Computation. Professor John Lawler.
CABA: Micro-Ed CONFER printout in record group does not seem complete.
CAP: SHARE ICPSR (Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research) summer symposia communication conference. Led to a permanent conference for CAP (Computer Assistance Program of the Political Science Department).
CAP:SUMMER Discussion on MTS and use of CONFER.
CPS:WORD Designed to serve as an online user's group for text processing software in general.
CRLT: AUC Conference set up for the Apple University Consortium Organization (AUC).
CRLT: CBE For discussion of issues related to computer-based education.
CRLT: Con.ED To discuss the educational applications of computer conferencing at the University of Michigan.
CRLT: EdMicro Discussion on use and thoughts of how microcomputers could be used in the classroom for teaching.
CRLT: Expos Self-reflection on writing experience. Classroom experiment with technology.
CRLT:HC Conference designed only for persons involved in planning the HyperCard Workshop.
CRLT: Hypercard Designed for discussion, organization and review of information relating to Hypercard.
CRLT:MAC.NOTES Conference for the discussion of the Macintosh computer in education.
CRLT:MERRA Conference designed for the activities of the Michigan Energy Resource and Research Association.
CRLT:MICROS Discussion on all aspects of microcomputers.
CRLT:OldMicros For a statewide discussion of the role of microcomputers in education.
CRLT:Organizer Designed to share ideas about the organization of conferences and the design of CONFER.
CRLT:Planning Conference developed out of MET:CAUSE for the purpose of developing a plan for the UM MTS user's conference (USER:FORUM).
CRLT:Religion Discussion conference for a religion class.
CRLT:Use.CONFER Conference set up to help UM faculty use CONFER.
CRLT: TA CONFER to discuss technology assessment
CRLT: USE.CONFER1 Discussion of how CONFER could be used in education.
CRLT: WORDP Conference designed to provide a forum for discussion on word processing applications.
CRLT: WS351 Conference for course on Women and the Community.
IEAR: Advisors Purpose stated as "an experiment, so we can explore, suggest and critique procedures related to electronic communicating."
ISTA All CONFERS starting with ISTA are conferences designed for the International Society for Technology Assessment conference held in Ann Arbor October 1976.
GULF:Forum Developed for a symposium titled "Learning from the War in the Persian Gulf," March 12-13, 1991. The CONFER was sponsored by the Horace H. Rackham Graduate School and the Information Technology Division. Purpose was to facilitate ongoing discussion on issues related to the events in the Persian Gulf.
LAW814 Conference for "Communication Sciences and Law" taught by Professor Layman Allen.
LAWC:MUSIC Discussion of issues related to computer music. Informal group formed within the Department of Electrical Engineering.
LINK:ART Public conference sponsored by the School of Art as an informal meeting place for students, faculty, and staff to share information and ideas on art.
LISA:MAC Information exchange with Apple University. [Does not seem to be complete.]
LOGO:FORUM Network for educators interested in LOGO. Includes participants from across Michigan.
MAC.NOTES A place to discuss anything related to the Macintosh computer.
MAYA:PEACE Peace Studies Conference.
MCUL:Forum Educators from across Michigan discuss computers and education.
MCUL:SIGCC Discussion involving high school teachers, information technologists, and administrators on the topic of technology and education.
MEET OURSELVES Discussion of health and health-related issues.
MEET: PLANNERS Set up as conference to administer MEET: STUDENTS.
MEET: STUDENTS First conference started and administered by students. Covers a range of topics.
MEET: UM Public conference with purpose of informing participants about the university community.
MICROS The conference for discussion of personal computers. Provided by the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching
MNET: CAUCUS Originally started in January 1976, it is thought to be one of the first public CONFERs. Its original focus was Merit Network.
MSTA: FORUM Conference developed by the Michigan Science Teachers Association to increase communications within the Michigan science community.
NOW: CONSIDER Electronic counterpart to Consider.
PC2: !CONF Conference designated for public domain and shareware files.
RP.CONFER First conference started on the MTS system by Robert Parnes. Parnes starts the conference by asking "if anyone has any good ideas about what we might discuss using teleconference." Participants included Al Adler, Merrill Flood, Karl Zinn, Manfred Kochen and Dan Ayers.
SSHD CONFER Conference designed for School of Nursing course 630.
SPSS: TALK Conference for users of the SPSS statistical package.
STAT: CON.CENSUS Designed to provide a toll for discussion of computer programs for statistics and their uses and to invite comment on the University Census of Statistical Programs.
WING: SPAN A conference for general women's issues.
USER: Forum and USER:OldForum For users to talk about information technology at the University.
USER: PLANNING Conference set up by Robert Parnes to evaluate USER: FORUM.
Related Material
Researchers interested in the development and use of information technology at the University of Michigan may also want to consult the following record groups and collections at the Bentley Historical Library:
Computing Center (University of Michigan) records
Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records
University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (University of Michigan) records
Vice-President for Research (University of Michigan) records
M-Pathways Project (University of Michigan) records
Bernard A. Galler papers
Aaron Finerman papers